Part 4. You will hear part of a presentation by an
urban planning student about the role of rivers in cities around the world. First, you have
some time to look at questions 31 to 40.
It's quite hard to think of a city that doesn't have a big river running through it. If you
think about the major cities in the world, Shanghai, New York, Mumbai, London, they're
nearly all built on rivers. When these cities were established hundreds or even thousands
of years ago, the rivers were a big part of people's lives. In 16th century London, the
quickest way to get from one part of the city to another was by river. But people also used
the river for fishing, as the water then was relatively clean, and they would also go on
boat trips up and down the river just for pleasure, as a relaxing escape from the noise
and bustle of the city streets. But as industries developed and populations increased, city
rivers suffered. The rising number of people meant there was a huge increase in the amount
of sewage discharged into the rivers. Rivers had always been used for this purpose, but
when the number of inhabitants was so small, that wasn't such a problem. However, as cities
grew to over a million inhabitants, the impact on the rivers became more serious. In addition,
other types of pollution increased as factories were built beside the river and discharged
their waste materials into the water. This got worse over time. As recently as 1957,
scientists at London's Natural History Museum declared that the River Thames was dead in
biological terms, as the water was too filthy to support any kind of life. But in recent
years, as rivers lost their industrial function, cities have begun to recognise their true
value and to take steps to clean them up. For example, the River Thames is now cleaner
than it's been for 150 years. These days you can see seals swimming in the water, and recently
people had to try to rescue a whale which had got lost and swum up the river from the
sea by mistake. Unfortunately they didn't succeed, but the problem was disorientation
rather than the quality of the water. Then, all around the world, riverside areas are
now seen as prime sites for development. Warehouses that were once used for storing goods are
now being converted into expensive restaurants and also into apartments with river views,
which are in great demand and sell for astronomical prices. In Los Angeles, on the west coast
of the USA, an architect has plans to revitalise the banks of the river and to make a park
there which can provide facilities for sports as well as a natural environment for relaxing
in. It's also hoped that the riverside can be used for other purposes. It's been proposed
that facilities could be provided for displaying projects related to various kinds of art that
have been produced by local people, for example. In the city of Paris, during the summer months
of July and August, all the traffic is banned from the roads by the sides of the river and
the banks are transformed into beaches where people can relax in deck chairs under potted
palm trees, sunbathe or buy a drink or a snack while enjoying the view.
But to make the most of our rivers in our increasingly crowded cities, we need to allow
them to regain their original purpose and be used as a means of transport, reclaiming
our streets from cars and lorries. To do this, we'll have to shift more traffic back
to the river but this time cleanly and silently, making the most of modern technology. Already
more than two billion passengers use the ferry to travel in cities around the world like
Istanbul, San Francisco and New York, and these numbers are set to rise further. Admittedly
it's not a fast way of travelling but neither is a car when it's stuck in traffic. Of course
passenger traffic on roads might decrease as more people start working from home but
another recent development, the huge rise in online shopping, has meant that another
form of urban traffic just keeps on growing and that's deliveries. Trucks and vans in
the city pollute and double-park while dropping off parcels. Imagine using the immense capacity
of shipping to take these trucks off the road. One freight barge can replace 44 large trucks,
uses far less energy and causes less pollution. When the barge docks at the riverside, the
parcels could be taken the last few kilometres to their final destination on cargo bikes
– electric ones of course. This is already happening in the Dutch city of Amsterdam and
in future the final stage could even be carried out by drone, although at present this isn't
allowed. Wouldn't it be great to unblock our city centres in this way? Looking further
ahead...
That is the end of part 4. You now have one minute to check your answers to part 4.
That is the end of the listening test. In the IELTS test you would now have 10 minutes
to transfer your answers to the listening answer sheet.